Data handling is extremely important.
As soon as we receive the assets, the data we need to protect.
We need to make sure we know the best practices for handling this data.
First, we need to recognize which assets we need to protect.
This is based on the value of the data.
According to the owner of that data, based on that,
we see what kind of risk we are facing with
respect to the likelihood that this information could be compromised,
destroyed or changed by any means and what
vulnerabilities exist that we need to account for.
This is the life cycle of data handling from create to store, to use, to share,
to archive and finally to destroy.
And at any point,
there are different risks to the data and different practices for handling it.
Some of these procedures are mandated by government standards,
for example, in the US, the Occupational Safety and Health administration,
OSHA is the federal government agency that protects the well being of workers
under the rules of the health care Insurance, Portability and Accountability Act.
Hi,
a
medical records need to be kept for 10 years.
But under OSHA, if we have a medical record of on the job injury,
that record needs to be maintained for over 30 years,
even after the last day of work in that particular organization,
that's regulatory requirement.
And if you don't know that or don't abide by it,
you can find yourself in trouble as the result of an audit.
So you can see that we have to be very cautious when deciding how to handle data.
As there may be multiple regulations that apply to a single piece of data.
Also in the US, there are specific guidelines related to the payment card industry,
data security standards, PC I DS S requirements regarding credit card information
and how to maintain that information securely
in the European Union.
The GDPR also has specific requirements regarding the handling of financial data.
In order to protect data properly,
you need to know all the relevant requirements for the
type of data being protected in the various geographic areas.
Many countries and other jurisdictions have regulations that require certain
data protections throughout every stage of the data's life cycle.
These govern how the data is acquired, processed,
stored and ultimately destroyed.
And when looking at the life cycle of the data,
we need to keep a watchful eye and protect the information at every stage,
even if it's ready to be legally destroyed at the end of the life cycle.
In some cases, multiple jurisdictions may impose rules affecting the data.
We are charged with protecting
in these instances we need to be aware of any and all regulations that affect us.
Some data handling practices include classification and labeling,
where you determine the sensitivity of the data,
what is available to everyone and what needs to be restricted
and label the information accordingly so that your
access controls will allow the correct level of access
retention is how long we store the information
and where based on the requirements of our organization
and perhaps regulatory agencies as well.
And then there needs to be defensible destruction,
meaning that we have the regulatory mandate backing
up our decision to destroy the data.
Destruction can be physical of hard drives or
computer chips or destruction of digital records,
which can be done under a number of methodologies.
We need to make sure we understand the secure destruction of the data because often
we think we can just empty the virtual trash can to delete the data.
But when we do that old emails and other data may never be erased,
to completely erase the data on physical media,
you need to choose some technical equipment for
degassing such as powerful magnets to erase the data stored on
tape and disk media such as computer and laptop hard drives,
diskettes, reels, cassettes and cartridge tapes.
However,
an individual with sophisticated equipment
could potentially still retrieve that information
at least partially.
So we must make sure we understand what recovery tools are available.
Because if you are subject to regulatory compliance,
you have to follow through with specific
protocols and processes to destroy that information
as required so that it can no longer be accessed in any way.